<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter, giving a descripton of the Isthmus of Darian (where the Scot's colonie is settled;) from a gentleman who lives there at present. With an account of the fertility of the soil, the quality of the air, the manners of the inhabitants, and the nature of the plants, and animals. &amp;c. And a particular mapp of the Isthmus, and entrance to the river of Darian.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48103</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1549</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216547</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828274</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828274</idno>
            <idno type="VID">32701</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48103)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32701)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1927:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter, giving a descripton of the Isthmus of Darian (where the Scot's colonie is settled;) from a gentleman who lives there at present. With an account of the fertility of the soil, the quality of the air, the manners of the inhabitants, and the nature of the plants, and animals. &amp;c. And a particular mapp of the Isthmus, and entrance to the river of Darian.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for John Mackie, in the Parliament-Closs [sic], and James Wardlaw on the north side of the street a little below the Cross, at the sign of the Bible,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M. DC. XC. IX. [1699]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Darien Scots' Colony, 1698-1700 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Darien (Panama and Colombia) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Panama --  History --  To 1903 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:32701:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32701:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER, giving A DESCRIPTION OF THE ISTHMUS OF DARIAN: (Where the SCOT'S <hi>COLONIE</hi> is ſettled;) From a <hi>GENTLEMAN</hi> who lives there at preſent.</p>
            <p>With an <hi>Account</hi> of the <hi>Fertilneſs</hi> of the <hi>Soil,</hi> The <hi>Quality</hi> of the <hi>Air,</hi> The <hi>Manners</hi> of the <hi>Inhabitants,</hi> And the <hi>Nature</hi> of the <hi>Plants,</hi> and <hi>Animals. &amp;c</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND A particular <hi>MAPP</hi> of the <hi>Iſthmus,</hi> and Entrance to the <hi>River</hi> of <hi>DARIAN.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Mackie,</hi> in the <hi>Parliament-Cloſs,</hi> and <hi>James Wardlaw</hi> on the North Side of the <hi>Street</hi> a little below the <hi>Croſs,</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>Bible.</hi> Prince 7 <hi>Pence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>M.DC.XC.IX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:32701:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:32701:2"/>
            <head>A <hi>LETTER, giving a</hi> Deſcription <hi>of the</hi> Iſthmus <hi>of</hi> Darian, (<hi>where the</hi> Scot's Colony <hi>is ſettled</hi>) <hi>from a</hi> Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman <hi>who lives there at preſent.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>COnform to your Deſire, and mine own Promiſe: I have ſent You the following Deſcription of <hi>Darian;</hi> I was up the Country when the two Gentlemen went for <hi>Scotland</hi> who brought the News of our arrival: but having now an Occaſion I have ſent you the following Account.</p>
            <p>You deſired a particular Account of the ſaid <hi>Darian,</hi> long ſince, And according to your Deſire, I have ſent a particular Account of the <hi>Nature</hi> of the <hi>Ground, Animals, Fruits,</hi> and <hi>Trees;</hi> and what <hi>Minerals</hi> they have, with a Draught of the Place, The <hi>Habits</hi> of their <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Queens,</hi> The <hi>Form</hi> of their <hi>Houſes,</hi> The <hi>Way</hi> of their <hi>Fighting</hi> with the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and other Enemies.</p>
            <p>Since our ſafe Arrival We have vieued, tranſverſ'd, and gone about near an hundered Miles in the Country formerly called <hi>Darian:</hi> but We have named it <hi>CALEDONIA,</hi> and there is a Fort very conveniently built, which We call <hi>New-EDINB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Isthmus</hi> of <hi>Darian</hi> is ſituated in the <hi>Main-Land</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>America,</hi> on the North of the <hi>Equinoctial Line,</hi> 8 <hi>degr.</hi> 11 <hi>min. Latitude;</hi> The Land is narrower from the <hi>North</hi> to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:32701:3"/>the <hi>South</hi> Sea, which you will ſee by the <hi>Mapp:</hi> As for the great <hi>River</hi> of <hi>Darian,</hi> it is ſituated ſomething to the <hi>Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> ot the <hi>Golden Iſland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The golden Iſland is but a ſmall place, not much bigger than <hi>Inch-Keith</hi> in the <hi>Firth</hi> of <hi>Forth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are a great many Iſlands weſtward from the golden Iſland 14. <hi>Leagues</hi> called <hi>Zanblas</hi> Iſlands.</p>
            <p>The Situation of our <hi>Fort</hi> does ly very conveniently, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a <hi>Bay</hi> upon the <hi>West,</hi> with many ſmall <hi>Rocks,</hi> which make it inacceſſable; On the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> the great River of <hi>Darian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Soil</hi> is as good here, as in any other place in <hi>America;</hi> up the Country there are long Ranges of <hi>Mountains,</hi> well cloathed with <hi>Trees,</hi> which for the moſt part are <hi>Palm,</hi> and <hi>Yellow-Sanders;</hi> The Inhabitants call it <hi>Bois de Chandle,</hi> or in Engliſh <hi>Candle-Wood;</hi> It burns like a Candle, and ſerves them with Light while they fiſh in the Night time. Here grows alſo <hi>Lignum ſanctum,</hi> or <hi>Guiacum,</hi> its Virtues are very well known, more eſpecially to thoſe who obſerve not well the VII. Commandment, and are giv'n to impure Copula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; Phyſicians drawing hence in ſeverall Compoſitions the greateſt Antidote againſt all venerall Deſeaſes, as alſo for cold and vitious Humors.</p>
            <p>The Tree likewiſe that affords <hi>Gummi Elemi</hi> grows here in great Aboundance; As doth <hi>Radix Chinae,</hi> or <hi>China-Root;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is a <hi>Prickle Palm,</hi> ſo call'd becauſe it is infinitly full of <hi>Prickles</hi> from the <hi>Root</hi> to the <hi>Leaves;</hi> with theſe Prickles the <hi>Indians</hi> uſe to torment the Priſoners they take in Battle, they tye them to a Tree, then takeing theſe Thorns they put them into little Pellets of Cotton dipt in Oil, and ſtick them
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:32701:3"/>in the Sides of the miſerable priſoners, as thick as the Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles of an <hi>Hedg-Hogg:</hi> which cauſe an incredible Torment to the Patient; Then they ſet them a Fire, and if the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented Priſoner ſing in the Midſt of his Torments: He is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem'd a couragious Soldier, who neither fears his Enemies nor the Torture; But if on the contrary, He cry out, they e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem him a Coward, and unworthy of any Memory. This Cuſtom was told me by an <hi>Indian,</hi> who ſaid He had uſed his Enemy thus, oftentimes. But to return to the <hi>Prickle-Palm,</hi> I ſhall only tell you that theſe Palm Trees in this only differ from the ordinary <hi>Palms,</hi> The <hi>Leaves</hi> are like theſe of other <hi>Palm</hi> Trees, only a little bigger, and rounder, and full of little <hi>Kernels,</hi> as pleaſeing to the Taſte as the <hi>Walnuts</hi> in <hi>Europe.</hi> The <hi>Wine-Palm</hi> is ſo call'd from the Aboundance of Wine gathered from it, of an extraordinary Shape or Form for from the <hi>Root</hi> up half Way, it is only three or four In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches thick; but upward, ſomething above two thirds of its Height; It is as big, and as thick, as an ordinary Bucket, &amp; within it is full of a certain Matter very like a ſlender Stock of white <hi>Cabbage,</hi> which is a very juicy of a Liquor much pleaſing to the Palate; This Liquor after Fermentation and Settling of the Grounds, becomes very good and clear Wine.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Fruit</hi> is much like to that of other <hi>Palms,</hi> but ſmaller, like <hi>Cherries;</hi> To write farther of the Trees, it would fill a great many Sheets; But I will only name them: <hi>Palm a Chapelet,</hi> or <hi>Roſary-Palm,</hi> ſo called by the <hi>French,</hi> and <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards; Caremit-Tree,</hi> very like our <hi>Pear-Tree,</hi> very pleaſing to the Taſte; <hi>Genpa-Trees,</hi> like to our <hi>Cherry Trees;</hi> beſides theſe, there are diverſe other Sorts of Trees, as <hi>Cedars</hi> in great Aboundance, which this Part of the World produces; They are very uſefull for building Ships and Canoa's, Theſe <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noa's</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:32701:4"/>are like little Ferry-Boats, being made only of one Tree hollowed, and fitted, for the Sea: They are ſo ſwift, that they may be called <hi>Neptun</hi>'s <hi>POST-HORSES.</hi> The <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians</hi> make theſe <hi>Canoa's</hi> without any Iron Inſtruments, by only burning the Trees nigh the Root, and then ſo govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the fire, as nothing is burnt more than what they would have; Some have <hi>Hatches</hi> of <hi>Flint</hi> wherewith they ſcrape or pare off whatſoever are burnt too far, and theſe by fire only they give that ſhape which renders them capable of naviga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting 60. or 80. <hi>Leagues</hi> with ordinary Security. Here is <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſile-Wood, Yaco</hi> is another Sort of Tree; Here are a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Cabbage-Trees,</hi> the <hi>Cabbage</hi> growing on the Top of it. Here grows the <hi>Coco-Nut,</hi> of which the <hi>Chacolat</hi> is made. Here grows the <hi>Pinn-Apple,</hi> and a great dale of <hi>Plantine,</hi> or <hi>Sugar-Canes,</hi> of which they make <hi>Sugar;</hi> And a great dale of other Trees, which being too tedious to give you an Account of, I forbear; You may have any <hi>Trees, Roots,</hi> or <hi>Herbs,</hi> that grow in <hi>Europe</hi> as well as others that will not grow there, as <hi>Mammi; &amp;c.</hi> You may have a great dale of <hi>Tobacco</hi> if you plant, much better than in any Place to the Northward.</p>
            <p>I ſhall give you an Account of the makeing <hi>Sugar</hi> &amp; <hi>Indigo</hi> in another place.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Flies</hi> as Inſects ſeverall Sorts of them, theſe are as big as Horſe-Flies in <hi>Enrepe,</hi> and denting themſelves upon Mens Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dys, ſtick and ſuck the Blood till they can no longer fly, which obliges the Inhabitants to wear continually Branches of Trees to Fan them away; There are a great dale of other Sorts, as <hi>Cochinilla</hi>'s; There are monſtruous <hi>Adders</hi> which are very frequent in theſe Places, upon which Account I durſt neverly on the Graſs; Here are very good Land <hi>Tortoiſes,</hi> which are very good meat; There are alſo <hi>Crocodiles,</hi> I could tell you, a good true ſtory about One of them, but being too tedious I forbear.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:32701:4"/>
            <p>There is a great dale of <hi>Doggs, Deer, Rabbets,</hi> and <hi>Monkeys,</hi> and many other Sorts of Quadrupeds, which Ye have not the like of in <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You have a great dale of all Sorts of Fowls many wherof do not breed in <hi>Europe,</hi> as <hi>Parrots;</hi> They make their Neſts in Holes of <hi>Palmito</hi> Trees, which Holes are before made by other Birds, for they are not capable of excavating any wood tho' never ſo ſoft, having their own Bills too crooked and blunt; Hence provident Nature hath ſupplyed them with the Labour of other Birds called <hi>Carpenteros,</hi> or <hi>Carpinters;</hi> Theſe are no bigger than <hi>Sparrows:</hi> Yet having ſuch hard and pierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Bills, that no Iron Inſtrument can be made fitter to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cavate any Tree, though never ſo ſolid, and hard; And theſe Holes the Parrots getting Poſſeſſion of build their Neſts.</p>
            <p>Of <hi>Pigeons</hi> of all Sorts we are aboundantly provided; There is another ſmall Bird here called <hi>Cabreros,</hi> or <hi>Goat-Keepers,</hi> and chiefly feed upon <hi>Crabs</hi> of the <hi>Sea;</hi> In theſe Birds are ſeaven diſtinct <hi>Bladders</hi> of <hi>Gall,</hi> and their Fleſh is as bitter as <hi>Aloes:</hi> Of theſe We have aboundance.</p>
            <p>There are very many <hi>Crows,</hi> or <hi>Ravens,</hi> more trouble<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome, than uſefull, who make a moſt hideous Noiſe.</p>
            <p>We have ſeveral fruits &amp; roots very uſefull, as <hi>Potat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> they dres them only by well boiling them in a Kettle, with fair clean water; Then we cover them with a Cloath for half an Hour where they become as ſoft as boiled <hi>Cheſnuts;</hi> Of the ſaid <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates</hi> we make a Drink called <hi>Maiz:</hi> They cut them into ſmall ſlices, and cover them with hot water; when they are well imbibed they preſs them through a courſe Cloath, and the <hi>Liquor</hi> that comes throgh tho ſomething thick they keep in Veſſels made for that Purpoſe; Hereafter ſettling two or three Days, it works: And having thrown off its <hi>Lees,</hi> is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:32701:5"/>fit for Drink They uſe with great Delight, and tho' it be ſomewhat four: Yet it is very pleaſant, ſubſtantial, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary wholſome; The Invention of this is wholly owing to the <hi>Indians,</hi> as well as many other things found out for the Preſervation of Mans Life.</p>
            <p>There is a Root called by the Indians <hi>Cazave</hi> of which they make a Liquor called <hi>Vey-Con</hi> much like unto <hi>Beer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another Fruit called <hi>Bananas,</hi> is an excellent Liquor, which in Strength, and Pleaſantneſs of Taſt, may be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the beſt Wines of <hi>Spain:</hi> But this Liquor eaſily cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes Drunkenneſs.</p>
            <p>VVe begin now to plant <hi>Tobacco</hi> for Trade; The Manner whereof is this: VVe make Bedds of Earth 12. Foot ſquare, theſe thay cover with <hi>Palmito</hi> Leaves, that the Rays of the <hi>Sun</hi> may not reach the Earth; Then we water them when it doth not rain, as we do our Gardens in <hi>Europe;</hi> Being grown about the Bigneſs of young <hi>Lettuce:</hi> we tranſplant it into ſtreight Lines in ſpacious Fields, ſetting every Plant 3. Foot diſtant from each other; The <hi>Tobacco</hi> muſt be weeded very carefully: ſeing the leaſt Root of any other Herb comeing near it hinders its Grouth.</p>
            <p>There is a ſort of Fiſh which the <hi>Indians</hi> many times eat of it is much like unto a <hi>Cow,</hi> becauſe its Head, Noſe, and Teeth, are very like to them; They are found commonly where under the Depth of the waters its full of Graſs, in w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ich its thought they feed; They have no Ears, but in place of them two little Holes, as wide as ones little finger; Near the Neck thy have two Finns, under which are two Uders like the Breaſt of a VVoman; The Skin is very cloſs, this Skin on the Back is two finger thick which being dryed is as hard as whalebone, and may ſerve to make walking ſtaffs
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:32701:5"/>the Belly is in all things like that of a <hi>Cow,</hi> as far as the <hi>Reins;</hi> their manner of engendring is the ſame with that of a land Cow, the Male being every way like that of a <hi>Bull;</hi> they conceave and breed but once, but what Time they go with <hi>Calf,</hi> I could learn; Theſe Fiſhes have a very acute Senſe of <hi>Hearing,</hi> ſo as in takeing them the fiſher-men make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not the leaſt Noiſe do not row unleſs very ſlightly, for this reaſon they uſe certain Inſtruments for Rowing, by the <hi>Indians</hi> called <hi>Pagayos</hi> with which they row without any Noiſe to fright the fiſh while they are a fiſhing they ſpeak not one to another only make ſigns, they dart them with Javelins having two Hooks at the End; Theſe fiſh are ordinarly from 20 to 24 Foot long; Their Fleſh is good to eat, being in like in colour to that of a land Cow, but in taſte to Pork It hath much <hi>Fat,</hi> or <hi>Greaſe,</hi> which We make Oil of.</p>
            <p>We have alſo another fiſh called <hi>Tortoiſe,</hi> of an indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Bigneſs, and of a green Colour, their Scales are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what hard, and of a very pleaſant Taſte; There is another Sort ſomewhat ſmaller; this Sort commonly keep themſelves among the Rocks, whence they crawl out for Food, which is generally <hi>Sea-Apples;</hi> Theſe other above mentioned, feed on <hi>Graſs,</hi> which grows in the Water on the ſandy Banks; Their Eggs are almoſt like theſe of a <hi>Crocodile,</hi> but without any <hi>ſhell,</hi> being only covered with a thin <hi>film;</hi> They are found in ſuch prodigious Quantitys along the ſhore, that were they not frequently deſtroy'd by Birds, the Seas would abound with <hi>Tortoiſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Way and Manner of fiſhing them is as follows; <hi>viz.</hi> by makeing a great Nail, or Kind of Dart; this they fix at the End of a long Pole, with which they kill the <hi>Tortoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> whenever they appear above Water.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:32701:6"/>
            <p>The <hi>Indians</hi> for the moſt part are very dextrous in takeing theſe <hi>Tortoiſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will give you an Account of our ſhooting of ſome <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keys,</hi> and <hi>Birds</hi> called <hi>Pheaſants;</hi> The Toil of ſhooting did ſeem, at leaſt to me, to be ſufficiently compenſated with the Pleaſure of killing the <hi>Monkeys,</hi> for at theſe We made ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narly 15 or 16 ſhot before We could kill three or four, ſo nimbly would they eſcape our Hands, and aim even after be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much wounded; On the other ſide it was a Diverſion to ſee the femal Monkeys carry their little Ones on their backs when any Perſon paſſed under the Trees-where theſe Monkeys are ſitting; They will commonly ſquirt their Excrements u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon our Heads and Cloaths; likewiſe if ſhooting at any, one happen to be wounded, the reſt flock about him, and do lay their Paws upon the Wound to hinder the blood from iſſuing forth, others gather <hi>Moſs</hi> from the Trees and thruſt into the Wound, and hereby ſtop the Blood; At other times they gather ſuch or ſuch <hi>Herbs,</hi> and cheuing them in their Mouth apply as Poultties, all which cauſed in Me great Admiration, ſeing ſuch ſtrange Actions in theſe irrational Creatures, which teſtified the fidelity and love they had for one another.</p>
            <p>I ſhall give you an Account, by the way, of the <hi>People;</hi> I have learned to ſpeak ſomewhat of the <hi>Language</hi> by One of them them who can ſpeak tolerable good <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I enquir'd into their <hi>Customs, Lives,</hi> and <hi>Policy:</hi> whereof I give you this Account; They are governed by a King, and ſeverall Princes: they have generally a great Hatred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> There are a great many perſons of them; they are very courtious to any that give them any thing. Here are two Sorts of People of them: The one Sort cultivates the Ground, and make Plantations; theſe are moſt numerous,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:32701:6"/>the other is a lazy ſort, never ſeen but at Night: They have <hi>Hutts</hi> that they live in all Day, till Night; they not care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for any other Habitation</p>
            <p>They uſe no other Cloaths than an <hi>Apron</hi> ty'd to their Middle, comeing down ſo as to hide their <hi>Privitys;</hi> ſuch Aprons are made of the <hi>Rinds</hi> of <hi>Trees,</hi> which they ſtrongly beat upon <hi>Stones</hi> till they are ſofned; The ſame they uſe for <hi>Bed-Cloaths,</hi> except a few who make them of <hi>Cotton,</hi> they are whiter than the whiteſt in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other is of a <hi>Browniſh</hi> Colour, but very handſome Bodys of <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Women</hi> tightly limb'd, the Men of them are verie dextruous at <hi>Bow</hi> and <hi>Arrow,</hi> and very good <hi>ſpears</hi> the common Sort uſe ſpears of <hi>Timber,</hi> the points are ſhod with <hi>Iron,</hi> or <hi>teeth</hi> of <hi>Crocodiles.</hi> They are moſt dextruous in <hi>Swimming,</hi> I did never ſee the like of them in <hi>Doucking</hi> for they will continue near half an Hour below the <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I could never learn what <hi>Religion</hi> they have, all I could learn was they neither believe in, nor ſerve the <hi>Devil:</hi> as many other Nations in <hi>America,</hi> do; Hereby they are not ſo much tormented by him as other Nations are. They are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry attentive at our Form of <hi>Worſhip;</hi> they did tell me they did not like <hi>Spaniards</hi> Religion, for they are as ill as thoſe that worſhip the <hi>Devil,</hi> for that Religion can not be good which is ſo cruel.</p>
            <p>Their ordinary Food conſiſts in ſeverall <hi>Fruits,</hi> a little in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian <hi>Corn;</hi> Fruits, ſuch as <hi>Bananas, Racoves, Ananas, Pota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos, Cazave;</hi> As alſo <hi>Crabs,</hi> and ſeverall <hi>Fiſh,</hi> which they kill in the fea with <hi>Darts,</hi> which they are wonderfully dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truous at.</p>
            <p>They are pretty expert in makeing certain pleaſant and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licat
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:32701:7"/>
               <hi>Liquors;</hi> The commoneſt among them is called <hi>Achioc,</hi> this is made of a certain <hi>Seed</hi> of <hi>Palm-tree,</hi> bruiſed and ſteept in hot water, till it be ſettled at the Bottom. This Liquor being ſtrain,d off, hath a pleaſant <hi>ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> and is very nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Other ſorts of liquors they prepare, which I ſhall omit for brevity; only I'll ſay ſomething of that made of <hi>Platanos</hi> Theſe they knead hot with water, and then put into great <hi>Calabaſhes,</hi> full of cold water for eight Days, during which it ferments as well as the beſt wine. This Liquor they drink for Pleaſure, and as a great Regale, ſo that when they invite any of their Friends, or Relations, they cannot treat them better than with this pleaſant Drink.</p>
            <p>They are very unskilful in dreſſing Victuals; ſo that they very ſeldom treat one another with Banquets. But when they invite others they deſire them to come and drink of their Liquors. Before the invited Perſons come to their Houſe, thoſe that expect them, comb their Hair verie well, and anoint their Faces with the Oil of <hi>Palm,</hi> mixt with a black Tincture which renders them very hideous, The women, alſo dawb their Faces with another Sort of Stuff, which makes them look is red as <hi>Crimſon.</hi> And ſuch are their greateſt Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Attire, Then He that invites, takes his Arms, which are three or four <hi>Azagayas,</hi> and goes out his <hi>Cottage</hi> 3 or 400 Steps, to wait for, and receive the invited perſons. As ſoon as they draw nigh, he falls down on the Ground, lying flat on his Face, without any Motion, as if he were dead; being thus proſtrat, the invited Friends take him up, and ſet him on his Feet, and go altogether to the <hi>Hutt.</hi> Here the Perſons invited, uſe the ſame Ceremony falling down to the Ground, as the Inviter did before. But he lifts them up one by one, and giving them his Hand, conducts them into his
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:32701:7"/>Cottage, where he cauſes them to ſit. The VVomen on theſe Occaſions uſe few, or no Ceremonys.</p>
            <p>Being thus brought into the Houſe, they are preſented every one with a <hi>Calabaſh,</hi> of about two <hi>Pynts</hi> of <hi>Scotiſh</hi> Meaſure, full of <hi>Achioc</hi> almoſt as thick as Water-Gruel, or Children-Pap. Theſe they are to drink off, and get down at any Rate.</p>
            <p>Theſe Calabaſhes being emptied, the Maſter of the Houſe, with many Ceremonys, goes about the Room, and gathereth his Calabaſhes. And this Drinking hitherto is reckon'd but one Wellcome. Afterwards, they drink of the <hi>Achioch</hi> above mention'd, to which they were invited.</p>
            <p>Then follow many Songs and Dances, and 1000 Careſſes, to the Women; So that oftentemes, for a Teſtimony of their great Love, they take their Darts, and with the points, they pierce and wound their genital parts. This I could believe, though often affirmed to me, till my own Eyes were Witt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of theſe and the like actions. Neither only on this Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion do they uſe this Ceremony of pierceing their Genitals, but alſo when they make love to any Woman, thereby to let them underſtand the Greatneſs of their Affection, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy.</p>
            <p>They marry not any young Maid without the Conſent of her Paients. If any deſires to take a Wife; he is firſt exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by the Damſels Father concerning feverall Sorts of good Husbandry. Theſe are commonly, whether He can make <hi>Azagayas,</hi> Darts for fiſhing; or ſpin a certain <hi>Thread,</hi> which they uſe about their Arrows. Having anſwered to Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, the Examiner cals to his Daughter, for a little <hi>Caba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſh</hi> full of <hi>Achioc.</hi> Of this he drinks firſt; then gives the <hi>Cup</hi> to the young Man; and He to the Bride, who drinks it out and with this only Ceremony the <hi>Marriage</hi> is made. When
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:32701:8"/>any one drinks to the Health of another, the ſecond Perſon is to drink out the Liquor, leſt in the <hi>Calabaſh,</hi> but in Caſe of Marriage, as was ſaid, it is conſum'd only among them three: And the Bride allways obtaining, by far, the greater ſhare.</p>
            <p>When the <hi>Woman</hi> lys in, neither She nor her Husband ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Time, coſtomarie among the <hi>Carribes;</hi> But as ſoon as the VVoman is delevered, ſhe goes to the next <hi>River, Brook</hi> or <hi>Fountain,</hi> and waſhes the new-born Creature, ſwathing it up in certain <hi>Rowlers,</hi> or <hi>Swath-Bands,</hi> there call'd <hi>Cabalas.</hi> This done ſhe goes about Her ordinarie Labour. When the <hi>Man</hi> dies, his Wife burys Him with all his <hi>Azagayas, Aprons,</hi> and <hi>Ear-Jewels;</hi> and comes every Day to her Husbands <hi>Grave</hi> bringing Him <hi>Meat,</hi> and <hi>Drink,</hi> for a whole <hi>Year</hi> after.</p>
            <p>Their <hi>Years</hi> they reckon by <hi>Moons,</hi> allowing fifteen to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Year, which makes their entire <hi>Circle,</hi> as our twelve <hi>Moneths,</hi> do ours.</p>
            <p>Some <hi>Writers</hi> of the <hi>Carribbe-Iſlands,</hi> affirm, that this <hi>Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony,</hi> of carrying of <hi>Victuals</hi> to the <hi>Dead,</hi> is generall among them; and that the <hi>Devil</hi> comes to the <hi>Sepulchres,</hi> and carries away the <hi>Meat</hi> and <hi>Drink.</hi> But I know the contrarie, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving my ſelf taken away theſe <hi>Offerings,</hi> and eaten them; for I knew that the <hi>Fruits</hi> uſed on theſe <hi>Occaſions,</hi> were of the choiceſt, and the <hi>Liquors</hi> of the beſt Sort. The Widow ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving compleated her <hi>Year,</hi> opens the <hi>Grave,</hi> and takes out all her Husbands <hi>Bones;</hi> Theſe ſhe ſcrapes, and waſhes very well &amp; puts them in a <hi>Cabala,</hi> or <hi>Satchel,</hi> &amp; is obliged for another <hi>year</hi> to carry them upon her Back all <hi>Day,</hi> and to ſleep upon them all <hi>Night,</hi> till the <hi>Year</hi> be out. Then ſhe hangs up the <hi>Bagg</hi> and <hi>Bones,</hi> againſt the <hi>Peſt</hi> of her own <hi>Door,</hi> if ſhe be a <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>streſſe</hi> of an <hi>Houſe,</hi> if not ſhe hangs them at the <hi>Door</hi> of her
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:32701:8"/>next Neighbour, or Relations.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Widows</hi> cannot marrie the ſecond time, according to their Cuſtoms, till after two <hi>Years</hi> End; the <hi>Men</hi> are bound to perform no ſuch <hi>Ceremonys</hi> for their <hi>Wives;</hi> But if anie <hi>Pirrat</hi> marrie an <hi>indian</hi> Woman, ſhe is bound to do in all things as if he were an <hi>Indian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall proceed now to give you an Account of the <hi>Men, Women,</hi> and their <hi>Habits;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They wear as an <hi>Ornament</hi> in their <hi>Noſes,</hi> a <hi>Gold,</hi> or <hi>Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-Plate,</hi> in <hi>Form</hi> of an <hi>Half-Moon;</hi> which when they drink, they hold up with one <hi>Hand,</hi> while they lift up the <hi>Cup</hi> with the other. The <hi>Men</hi> paint themſelves ſometimes with <hi>Streaks</hi> of <hi>Black,</hi> and the <hi>Women</hi> with <hi>Red.</hi> The <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> have in their <hi>Noſes</hi> a pretty thick <hi>Ring</hi> of <hi>Gold</hi> or <hi>Silver</hi> and cover themſelves with a <hi>Blanket</hi> only. They are general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly well featured: Among whom I ſaw ſeverall fairer than the faireſt in <hi>Europe,</hi> with <hi>Hair</hi> as white as the fineſt <hi>Flax.</hi> 'Tis reported of them, that they ſee better in the Dark, than in the Light.</p>
            <p>I ſhall further give You an Account of our going up the country to their <hi>King</hi> or chief <hi>Captain;</hi> we marching from our <hi>Fort</hi> with Captain <hi>Andraeas,</hi> and other of their <hi>Princes:</hi> We began our March towards their head Place, where their <hi>King</hi> reſided, firſt through a ſmall Skirt of a <hi>Wood,</hi> and then over a <hi>Bay</hi> almoſt three <hi>Miles,</hi> or a <hi>League</hi> in Length. After that We went about ſix or ſeaven <hi>Miles</hi> up a woody <hi>Valley,</hi> and We ſaw here and there ſome old <hi>Plantation,</hi> and had a very good Path to march in. There we came to the ſide of a <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi> which in moſt places was dry, and built Us <hi>Houſes,</hi> or rather <hi>Hutts,</hi> to lodge in.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Indians</hi> forbad us to ly upon the <hi>Graſs,</hi> for Fear of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:32701:9"/>monſtruous <hi>Adders,</hi> which are very fiequent in thoſe places.</p>
            <p>Breakeing ſome of the <hi>Stones</hi> that lay in the <hi>River,</hi> We found them ſhine with <hi>Sparks</hi> of <hi>Gold;</hi> Theſe Stones were driven down from the neighbouring <hi>Mountains</hi> in Time of <hi>Floods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next day of our March We mounted a very ſteep <hi>Hill,</hi> and on the other ſide, at the <hi>Foot</hi> thereof, We reſted on the <hi>Bank</hi> of a <hi>River,</hi> which Captain <hi>Andraeas</hi> told us, ran into South <hi>Sea,</hi> being the ſame River on which the Town of <hi>Santa Maria</hi> was ſituated. Hence We continued our March till a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Noon,</hi> and then aſcended another Mountain, far high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than the former; Here We were often, and in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in great Danger, the Mountain being ſo nigh to a <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendicular,</hi> and the <hi>Path</hi> ſo narrow, that but one Man at a Time could paſs, We arrived in the <hi>Evening</hi> on the other Side of ihe Mountain, and lodg'd again by the Side of the ſame River.</p>
            <p>Next <hi>Morning,</hi> We march'd all along the River aforemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd, croſſing it often, almoſt at ev'ry half Mile, ſometimes up to the <hi>Knees,</hi> and at other times up to the Middle, in a very rapid current. About Noon we came to a place, where we found ſome <hi>Indian</hi> Houſes. Theſe were very large, and neat: The ſides were built of <hi>Cabbage</hi>-Trees, and the Roofs of wild: <hi>Canes,</hi> thatch'd with <hi>Palmito-Royal;</hi> They had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Partitions, or diſtinct Ground-Roomes, but no Aſcent by <hi>Stairs.</hi> At this place were four of theſe Houſes together, all within a Stone's throw of one another, each of them have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a large <hi>Plantan</hi> Walk before it. Half a Mile from this place, liv'd the <hi>King,</hi> or chief <hi>Captain</hi> of the <hi>Indians</hi> of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> whe came to viſit Us in Royal <hi>Robes,</hi> with his <hi>Queen.</hi> and <hi>Family.</hi> His <hi>Crown</hi> was made of ſmall white <hi>Reeds</hi> cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:32701:9"/>woven, having no other <hi>Top</hi> than its lineing, which was red <hi>Silk.</hi> Round about the middle of it was a thin plate of <hi>Gold,</hi> about two Inches broad, lac'd behind, in which ſtuck two or three <hi>Oſtrich</hi> Feathers. About this Plate went alſo a Row of golden Beads, which were bigger than ordinar <hi>Peaſe;</hi> underneath which was ſeen the red lining of the <hi>Crown.</hi> In his Noſe he wore a large Plate of Gold, in Form of an half-<hi>Moon;</hi> and in each Ear a great gold Ring, nigh four Inches diameter with a round thin plate of Gold of the ſame Breadth, having an ſmall Hole in the Center, by which it hung to the Ring. He was covered with a thin white <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> Robe, reaching to the ſmall of his <hi>Leggs,</hi> and round its Bottom a Frienge of the ſame, three Inches deep; ſo that by reaſon of the length of this Robe, We could ſee no farther than his naked <hi>Anckles.</hi> In his Hand He had a long bright <hi>Lance</hi> as ſharp as any Knife. With Him He had three Sons each of them having a white Robe, and their Lances in their Hands, but ſtanding bare-headed before Him; as alſo did eight or nine Per ons more of his Retinue, or Guard.</p>
            <p>His <hi>Queen</hi> wore a red <hi>Blanket,</hi> which was cloſly girt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout her <hi>waſt,</hi> and another that came loſely over her head and ſhoulders. She had a young child in her Arms, &amp; two Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters walked by her, with their Faces almoſt covered with ſtripps, or ſtreaks of red, and about their Necks, and Armes almoſt loaden with ſmall Beads of ſeverall Colours. Theſe <hi>Indian</hi> Women of <hi>Darian,</hi> are generally very free, airy, &amp; brisk; yet withall very modeſt, and cautious in their Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands Preſence, of whoſe Jealouſie they ſtand in Fear. With theſe <hi>Indians</hi> We made an Exchainge, or had a Truck, as it is called, for <hi>Knives, Pins, Needles,</hi> or any ſuch-like Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles; but in our Dealing with them we found them to be very cunning.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:32701:10"/>
            <p>He gave Us a Calabaſh full of Liquor which they make of <hi>Plantans;</hi> This ſort of Fruit is firſt reduced to <hi>Maſh,</hi> then laid betwixt Leaves of the ſame Tree, and ſo uſed with Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer. After which Preparation, they call it <hi>Miſcelaw.</hi> On our March hither We found in our Way, here, and there, an Houſe or two, whoſe Owners commonly ſtood at the door and gave, as we Paſſed by, to every one of Us, either a ripe <hi>Plantan,</hi> or elſe a <hi>Cazave,</hi> or ſome other ſweet and pleaſant <hi>Root.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Captaine or King, is the head of their other Captains when they go to Battle againſt the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> ſomewhat to the South-ward of this Place is a pleaſant <hi>Plain,</hi> the generall. Place the <hi>Indians</hi> rendez-vous in.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now give You an Account of the reſt of their <hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Captain <hi>Ambroſio</hi> commands from the River <hi>Pinas, Bono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos, Mango,</hi> and <hi>Cocos,</hi> to the <hi>Samblas,</hi> He is a Man above ſixty, but ſtrong and vigorous, a mortall Enemy to the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards,</hi> with whom He has had long <hi>War;</hi> He is eſteem'd the braveſt, and moſt ſuccesfull of all their Commanders on every Occaſion; He's of a middle Size, well made, ſtrongly limb'd, and of a grave, and ſomewhat ſtern Countenance.</p>
            <p>He has a Son in law, one <hi>Pedro,</hi> a brisk little Fellow who ſpeaks good <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> haveing been a Slave to them at <hi>Panama</hi> for ſeverall Years, and who can never forget, nor forgive, their Uſage of him there.</p>
            <p>Captain <hi>Diego</hi> commands from the Bottom of the Gulph of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>raba</hi> on this ſide to <hi>Caret</hi>-Bay, and has about 3000. Men under his Command; He is eſteem'd the moſt powerfull a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, and has been at War with the <hi>Spaniard</hi> about
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:32701:10"/>a twelve Month. The Occaſion was this: The <hi>Indians</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veing found three Gold Mines within his Juriſdiction, being two ſmall ones, and a very great Vein, conſulted with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves what to do; And being ſenſible that they did not underſtand how to work them, concluded to diſcover them to the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> provided they'd allow them ſuch a ſhare of the Profit. This was agreed to, and faithfully promiſed by the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> but no ſooner had the <hi>Indians</hi> ſhew'd the <hi>Mines</hi> but they ſhut up two of them, and put ſtrong guards upon them, and fell to work upon the third, of which the <hi>Indians</hi> demanding their ſhare, they beat and abuſed them, calling them their Slaves, and threatned to exterminat them, which provock'd them ſo, that a little time after, they ſiez'd upon 20. <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and 3. <hi>Priests,</hi> and cut them all to pieces.</p>
            <p>The next to <hi>Diego,</hi> is one Captain <hi>Powſigo</hi> of <hi>Caret</hi>-Bay, He is one of the <hi>Indian</hi> Clergy-Men, and commands that Part of the Coaſt which lyes between <hi>Caret</hi>-Bay, and golden Iſland; He is but a ſmall Captain; and Brother in Law to <hi>Andraeas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Peninſulae</hi> which we poſſeſs, and which we found un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inhabited (nor has it ever been by any heretofore, that we have yet hear'd of,) lys betwixt his Bounds, and Captain <hi>Andraeas</hi>'s.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Golden-Iſland,</hi> to the River <hi>Pinas;</hi> about a <hi>League</hi> to the <hi>Weſt-ward</hi> of the <hi>Iſle</hi> of <hi>Pinas, Andraeas,</hi> and his Brother <hi>Pedro</hi> command, they are greater than <hi>Powſigo,</hi> but not ſo powerfull as <hi>Diego;</hi> yet their united Intereſts by Conſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinity, together with the Vicinity of their Commands to our Settlement, makes their Friendſhip of much greater Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:32701:11"/>
            <p>Theſe People have had a good Correſpondence, for ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>Years</hi> paſt, with the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and have ſuffered ſome of them to reſide among 'em to give an Account by Land to <hi>Panama,</hi> from time to time, who were upon this Coaſt about two months before our Arrivall here.</p>
            <p>Captain <hi>Ambroſio,</hi> who has the adjoyning Command, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced them to enter into the common Confederacy, and cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t off ten <hi>Spaniards</hi> who lived on the <hi>Main</hi> of the golden-Iſland, I diſtinguiſh it thus, by reaſon the Natives call all the <hi>Main</hi> oppoſite to the Iſland, by the ſame Name that it bears. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a League from the Water ſide there is an high Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain wherein they aſſure Us are ſeverall <hi>Mines</hi> of excellent <hi>Gold.</hi> The <hi>Spaniards</hi> are very ſenſible of this, and from time to time have taken great Care by fair or ſoul Means, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to let them be opned, well knowing that (being ſo near the <hi>North-ſea</hi>) they ſhould have the leaſt ſhare of them to themſelvs.</p>
            <p>Captain <hi>Andraeas</hi> has often been at <hi>Panama,</hi> the <hi>Mines</hi> of <hi>Sauta Maria,</hi> and the <hi>South-Sea;</hi> The <hi>Spaniards</hi> believeing he might be uſefull to them, made Him a Captain, by giveing Him a ſtick tip't with Silver, upon which He values himſelf above others, and that has (we are apt to believe) endeared Him to their Intereſts; yet the Love of ones Country, and Liberty is ſo naturall, that we have good Reaſon to believe that as ſoon (being a ſenſible cunning Fellow) as He finds we are able to protect Him, he will heartily join to our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt.</p>
            <p>Captain <hi>Pedro</hi> is eſteemed by <hi>Ambroſio,</hi> and all his People whoſe Daughter he has to VVife, as alſo two of her Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters by himſelf, which is allowed here, yet it ſeems that they believe it a Crime, ſince if they have any children during the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:32701:11"/>Life of their mother, they are buried alive, (I mean the child ren) which is very ſtrange, that the innocent ſhould ſuffer for the guilty.</p>
            <p>They preſt Us very hard to come and live by them, as alſo joyntly to make war with the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> whom they would engage upon the Forfaulture of their Heads, if we would aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt them with an hundered arm'd Men, and as many Arms, with 2000. of their own People, to drive. not only out of the <hi>Mines,</hi> (which are but three Days Journey from this Place,) but even out of <hi>Panama</hi> it ſelf. VVe gave them fair words, and promiſed to go to the <hi>West-ward</hi> with them to vieu the Coaſts, and if there were any convenienter Harbour for our ſhips, we would be their Neighbours.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Sanblaz</hi> to the River <hi>Conception,</hi> is commanded by one <hi>Corbet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next to <hi>Corbet</hi> from the River <hi>Conception,</hi> is one <hi>Nicola,</hi> a Man who ſpeaks <hi>Spaniſh</hi> as well as any naturall <hi>Spaniard,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been for about a dozen of Years of his Youth among them; He likewiſe reads and writes it perfectly, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands the State of <hi>Europe</hi> very well: which none other of them have any Notion of; He is ſaid to be wiſe and extrem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beloved by his People, for his Juſtice, and good Nature, in ſo much that there has been Deſigns to cut off <hi>Ambroſio,</hi> and place Him in his Room, for He is of a rough military temper, and often upon ſlight pretinces makes bold to take away what they have from them; However if they do not love him, they fear him, and his near Alliance, and ſtrick Friendſhip with <hi>Diego</hi> in the Gulph, a powerfull, and gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant old Fellow, renders Him very ſecure.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Nicola</hi> was in good Terms with the <hi>Spaniards</hi> till a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a twelve Month agoe, a Triffle made Him brake with them: and 'twas this;</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:32701:12"/>
            <p>He had got an excellent French <hi>Fuzie</hi> from a <hi>Buccanier,</hi> which He valu'd extremly: 'Twas ſomewhat out of Order, nor did He know how to right it again; A Spaniſh <hi>Don</hi> from <hi>Porto-Bello</hi> being at his Houſe, told him he would car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it with Him, and get it mended for Him, which the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſenting to, with a Deſire it might be return'd as ſoon as poſſible, They parted. The <hi>Don</hi> ſhew'd it to the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, who liked it extremly, and ſaid 'twas too good for an Heathen; So ordered an old ruſty <hi>Match-Lock</hi> to be ſent in Lieu. This He took ſo hainouſly, that He fell upon the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> wherever He ſound 'em, and cut them off, neither is He to be reconſil'd to them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ambroſio</hi> who all the reſt allow to be the moſt dareing, and brave, as alſo the moſt faithful to his Promiſe; being a true Friend, and a moſt inveterat Enemy to the <hi>Spaniards:</hi> keeps Him within Bounds.</p>
            <p>From the mouth of the River <hi>Coco,</hi> about a good League We went to <hi>Ambroſio</hi>'s Houſe, it ſtanding upon the Bank of this River, with about ten or a Dozen leſſer Houſes about it. When We came near, <hi>Ambroſio</hi> advanc'd about fifty Paces, with twenty Followers, all cloath'd in white looſe <hi>Frocks,</hi> with <hi>Frienges</hi> round the Bottom, and <hi>Lances</hi> in their Hands.</p>
            <p>He ſaluted Us kindly, and gave Us a Calabaſh full of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor almoſt like <hi>Lambs-Wool,</hi> which they call <hi>Miſhlow,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made of Indian <hi>Corn,</hi> and <hi>Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tatoes.</hi> This they get drink withall often; Before the houſe, about twenty Paces it was very ſmooth and clean. The houſe was about <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0. Foot in Length, 35. in Breadth, and 30. in Height. I was curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ovſly thatch'd with <hi>Palmetto-Royal,</hi> and over that <hi>Cajan</hi> Leavs, The <hi>Floor</hi> was of a firm <hi>Earth,</hi> like <hi>Tarras,</hi> very ſmooth, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:32701:12"/>clean. The <hi>Sides</hi> were of large <hi>Canes,</hi> about the Bigneſs of a Mans Legg, and near an <hi>Inch</hi> aſunder.</p>
            <p>In this Houſe live <hi>Ambroſio,</hi> and <hi>Pedro</hi> with their whole Familys, in all about 40. Perſons.</p>
            <p>There was an old Woman who cook'd their Victuals for them, and was very ſtirring about the Houſe; She ſeem'd to Us to be near ſixty. (and was <hi>Ambaoſio</hi>'s Grand-Mother) but upon asking Her Age, We were in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orm'd She was an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and twenty; We could not believe it, and were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded they muſt miſtake in the Computation of Time: but as an infallible Demonſtration, they ſhew'd to Us the ſixth Generation of this Womans Body in the Houſe, which was indeed very ſurpriſeing; And we were aſſured 'twas common amongſt them to live 150. or 60. Years; Yea 'tis obſerved thoſe of them who converſe often with the <hi>Europeaus,</hi> &amp; drink their ſtrong Liquors, are ſhort liv'd</p>
            <p>While We ſtay'd there, <hi>Ambroſio,</hi> and <hi>Pedro</hi> went out with their <hi>Guns</hi> to kill ſome <hi>Fowl</hi> for Us; <hi>Pedro</hi> return'd with ſome <hi>Partridges,</hi> the largeſt, and beſt that e're I ſaw, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bigger than our <hi>Capons,</hi> and exceeding ſweet.</p>
            <p>On <hi>November</hi> 30. Captain <hi>Andraeas</hi> came a-board the St. <hi>Andrew,</hi> We waiting an Oportunity of clearing ſome Suſpicions We had of his Correſpondence with the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> We taxt Him with it, and He ingeniouſly confeſt that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> had been friendly to Him, and had made Him a <hi>Captain;</hi> that He was obliged for his Safty to keep fair with them, They aſſureing Him We were nothing but <hi>Privateers,</hi> who had no Deſign to ſettle, but to plunder both <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and <hi>Indians,</hi> and be gone in two or three Months time, as they uſed to do, and if ſo, if He aſſiſted Us in any Meaſure,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:32701:13"/>as ſoon as We were gone, they'd deſtroy both Him, and His.</p>
            <p>VVe gave Him all poſſible Aſſurances of the Contrary, ſo that He was fully ſatisfied, and deſired we would give Him a <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> and receave Him, and his People into our Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; which if we did, He'd give Us all his Right to his part of the Country. VVhereupon a <hi>Commeſſion</hi> was ordered for Capt. <hi>Andraeas,</hi> and being read and approven of, it was delivered to Him.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Commiſſion</hi> being read, and rendered <hi>Verbatim</hi> to Him in <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> He agreed to every <hi>Article:</hi> then before 7 or 8 of his own People, and ſeverall of ours, it was delivered unto Him with a broad basked-hilted <hi>Sword,</hi> and a Pair of <hi>Piſtolls,</hi> with which He ſolemly promiſed to defend Us to the laſt <hi>Dropp</hi> of His Blood, againſt all our Enemys.</p>
            <p>Upon Advice of the <hi>K.</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi>'s Indiſpoſition, <hi>Count Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizeuma</hi> Vice-Roy of <hi>Mexico,</hi> born in that Kingdom, and of the Race of theſe great Emperors, had made ſuch an Intereſt that 'tis not to be doubted that he will ſpeedily ſet up for himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Carthagean</hi> has likewiſe been in a civil <hi>War,</hi> which is only covered, not quencht.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Porto-Bell</hi> about 700. Slaves got into a Body, which in a little time encreaſt to above 1500. The Governour not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to ſuppreſs them, was forced to come to very diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honourable Terms, <hi>viz.</hi> to allow them to be a free People, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and only call'd their Friends.</p>
            <p>Captain <hi>Powſigo</hi> of <hi>Caret</hi>-Bay, told us of ſeverall <hi>Gold-Mines</hi> within two Miles of us, and ſhew'd us a <hi>Sample</hi> of the <hi>Gold,</hi> which was extraordinary fine.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
